Friends of the Smith College Libraries Oral History Project, 1977-1982
Smith College Archives
1977-1982
Friends of the Smith College Libraries Oral History Project
RG 100
33 audio-cassette tapes
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
This collection reveals the memories about Smith College by several faculty, students, and staff ranging from the early twentieth century through mid twentieth century using oral history.
The Friends of the Smith College Library was formed in March 1942 to assist the Smith College Library's collection of material. In the 1977 fall meeting of the Committee of the Friends, the Oral history project was approved, and Gertrude Smith (1928) Professor Emeritus of Music, coordinated the task of recording "the recollections and reminiscence of retired members of the faculty and administrative staff who live in the Northampton area" (1976-1977 Annual Report). According to the annual reports, there were a total of 38 tapes; however, not all have survived.
The tapes range from personal recollections about being a student, staff, or faculty member at Smith to wider social and political issues of the times. The tapes record various changes in Smith College's landscape- the razing of buildings as well as changes in curriculum, departments, and staff. Gertrude Smith's summary provides a concise overview, highlighting key topics on each tape and noting whether the tape is single or double sided.
The following tapes mentioned in Smith's summary were never added to the collection:
Mrs. [Laura] Scales' Recollections, Jan. 28, 1977
Establishing the Archives and Sophia Smith Collection, Feb. 10, 1977
English Department Recollections, Feb. 11, 1977
Music Department Recollections, Mar. 22, 1977
Helen Hills Chapel and Religious Life, May 31, 1977
It is unclear whether the Ada Comstock Scholars tape does have a separate recording of Alice Dickinson with Eleanor Rothman and a group of Ada Comstock Scholars or whether the record of Eleanor Rothman with Adas Susan Donovan-Yarde (1980), Lorna Maclachlan (1980), and Phyllis Paige (1980) is the same record. The summary suggests the later.
The records are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
The Friends of the Smith College Libraries Oral History Project tapes were donated after the project was completed in 1983.
- Mrs. [Laura] Scales' Recollections of her experience as an undergraduate and as Warden: Jan. 28, 1977, Laura W. Scales (1901), Warden of College 1922-44; Eleanor Lincoln, Faculty member 1934-68 (Folder 1)
- Establishing the Archives and the Sophia Smith Collection: Feb. 10, 1977, Margaret S. Grierson (1922) Faculty member 1930-6; Marine Leland, Faculty member 1924-65 (Folder 2)
- English Dept. Recollections: Jan. 28, 1977, Charles J. Hill, Faculty member 1932-36; Eleanor Lincoln, Faculty member 1934-68, Assist. to the Dean 1942-43, Class Dean of 1944 and 1959 (Box C130, Folder 3)
- Music Dept. Recollections: March 22, 1977, John W. Duke, Faculty member 1923-67; Gertrude P. Smith (1928) Faculty member 1935-71 (Box C130, Folder 4)
- English Dept. Recollections: May 11, 1977, Katherine Hornbeak, Faculty member 1930-62; Edna Williams, Faculty member 1930-64 (Box C132, Folder 5)
- Helen Hills Chapel and religious life on campus: May 31, 1977, Vernon Gotwals, Faculty member 1952-84; Richard P. Unsworth, Faculty member and College Chaplin 1954-64, 1967-80 (Box C132, Folder 6)
- Religion Dept. Recollections: Aug. 4, 1977, J. Seelye Bixler, Faculty member 1924-33, Trustee 1963-70; Virginia Corwin, Faculty member 1930-39,1942-66 (Box C134, Folder 7)
- Financial Aid Office Recollections: Oct. 10, 1977, Mary Mensel (1918), Warden's Office 1923-46, Dir. of Scholarships and Student Aid 1946-64; Helen K. Milbank (1931), Assist. to the Pres. 1953-55 (Box C135, Folder 8)
- Biological Sciences Dept. Recollections: Dec. 19, 1977, Eleanor V. Smith, Faculty member 1926-69, Dir. of Science Center 1966-69, Class Dean of 1948 and 1958; Lois Te Winkel, Faculty member 1933-68 (Box C136, Folder 9)
- History Dept. Recollections: March 1, 1978, Leona Gabel, Faculty member 1923-63, Class Dean 1932; Nelly Hoyt, Faculty member 1949-90; Anna Ahrens (1978); Elizabeth Carroll (1978) (Box C137, Folder 10)
- Chemistry Dept. Recollections: March 7, 1978, Milton Soffer, Faculty member 1942-77; Kenneth Hellman, Faculty member 1942- (Box C138, Folder 11)
- Mathematics Dept. Recollections: March 22, 1978, Alice B. Dickinson, Faculty member 1959- Dean of the College 1973-76; Neal McCoy, Faculty member 1931-70 (Box C139, Folder 12)
- Theatre Dept. Recollections: May 10, 1978, Charlotte Fitch (1934), Faculty member 1948-76, Dir. of Graduate Studies 1975-76; Denton N. Snyder, Faculty member 1945-80 (Box C140, Folder 13)
- Alumnae Recollections: May 15, 1978, Katharine Cowen (1920), General Sec. Alumnae Assoc. 1950-62; Laura Hodgkinson (1922), Pres. Alumnae Assoc. 1950-53, Trustee 1958-64, Chairman of the Board of Trustees 1961-64 (Box C141, Folder 14)
- Miss Macdonald's experience of three Smith College Presidents, first, as an undergraduate under Mr. Neilson, then as Secretary to Mr. Wright and Mr. Mendenhall: May 30, 1978, Florence Macdonald (1932), Sec. to the Dean 1948-50, Sec. to the Pres. 1950-76; Helen Milbank (1931), Assist. to the Pres. 1953-55 (Box C142, Folder 15)
- Alumnae Recollections: June 6, 1978, Frona Brooks Rice (1922) M.A 1934, Assist. in various college offices 1932-34, 1952-56 (Box C143, Folder 16)
- Foreign Students Committee Recollections: June 13, 1978, Edna Williams, Faculty member 1930-64, Chairman of Committee on Foreign Students 1956-59; Joan Bramwell, Faculty member 1957-92 Chairman of Foreign Students Committee 1974-80 (Box C144, Folder 17)
- Smith Faculty Recollections: Jan. 17, 1978, Helen Russell, Dean of Students; Margaret Zelljadt, Faculty member 1968- Dean of Class of 1980,1977, 1984 (Box C145, Folder 18)
- Ada Comstock Scholars: Feb. 15, 1979; April 1976; April 21, 1976, Eleanor Rothman, Faculty member 1956-62 Assist Dir./ Dir. of Ada Comstock Scholars Program 1975-2004; Alice Dickinson, Dean; Susan Donavan-Yarde (1980); Lorna Maclachlan (1980); Phyllis Paige (1980) (Box C146, Folder 19)
- Service Organizations of Smith Recollections: April 4, 1979, Rita Wilkins, Dir of Voluntary Services; Susan Harris (1979), Chairman of S.O.S. (Box C147, Folder 20)
- Physical Education Dept. Recollections: May 16, 1979, Martha Clute (1948), Faculty member; Caryl Newof M.A. (1951), Faculty member (Box C148, Folder 21)
- Career Development Office Recollections: Feb. 18, 1979, Alice N. Davis (1930), Dir. of Vocational Office 1947-72; Mary Albro (1936), Dir. of Career Development Office 1972-81 (Box C149, Folder 22)
- Autobiographical Account of Samuel A. Eliot (Theater Dept.): Feb. 18, 1979, Samuel A. Eliot, Faculty member 1918-61; Elizabeth Hatch, Actress, Dancer, Theater Critic (Box C150, Folder 23)
- Government Dept. Recollections: Jan. 18, 1980, Peter Rose, Faculty member 1960-2003 Dir. of Social Science Research Center 1964-68; Leo Weinstein, Faculty member 1952-91 (Box C151, Folder 24)
- Art Dept. Recollections: Jan. 24, 1980, Phyllis Lehmann, Faculty member 1946-79; Elliot Ofner, Faculty member1960-2004 (Box C152, Folder 25)
- The Smith College Health Services Department: Feb. 5, 1980, Dr. Vera Joseph, College Physician and Dir. of Health Service 1964-75; Dr. Doris Sumerson, College Physician and Dir. of Health Service 1973-80 (Box C153, Folder 26)
- The Smith-Northampton Summer School: May 25, 1980, Lawrence A. Fink, Coordinator, Faculty member 1963-92; Francis L. Gougeon, Director (Box C154, Folder 27)
- Lewis-Emerson Fund-a confidential fund for needy students: Dec. 9, 1980, Laura L. Scales (1901), Warden of the College 1922-44 (Box C154, Folder 28)
- Alum. Assoc. 100th Anniversary: March 5 and 29, 1981, Gertrude Ridgway Stella (1937), Executive Dir. of the Alumnae Association 1964-1985; Ruth Jeffers Wellington (1945), Pres. of the Association 1975-78 (Box C155, Folder 29)
- M.A. Program in Italian Art Recollections: June 5, 1981, Agnes Mongan, M.A. Smith (1929) curator, then Asst. and Associate Dir. of the Fogg Museum at Harvard; Clarence and Ruth Kennedy (Box C156, Folder 30)
- The William Allen Neilson Library Recollections: June 25, 1981, Mary Ankudowich (1939), Librarian of the Werner Josten Library of the Performing Arts 1943-83; Ruth Richmond (1936), Dept. Head of Accessions and Gifts; Emma Kaplan, Assist Ref. Librarian 1942-79 (Box C157, Folder 31)
- Counselors, Trustees: Oct. 12, 1981, Helen Huberth Keene (1928), Counselor 1956-60, Trustee 1965-69; Nell Cochrane Taylor (1951), Counselor 1968-78, Trustee 1979- (Box C158, Folder 32)
- Planning renovation and expansion of Neilson Library: Jan. 14, 1982, Billie R. Bozone, College Librarian 1968-91; Charles Henderson, Faculty member 1964-86 (Box C159, Folder 33)
- Psychology Dept. Recollections: Jan. 20, 1982, Lisa Siipola, Faculty member 1921-73; Frances Volkman, Faculty member 1965- (Box C160, Folder 34)
- Faculty shows Recollections: May 10, 1982, Prof. John Duke's talk to OBND Meeting and excerpts from a faculty show "Love among the Ruins.", Faculty member 1923-67 (Box C161, Folder 35)
- Alumnae Recollections: Jan. 1983, [Elizabeth] Betty Webster (1912) contrasts world of 1908-12 with 1983 (Box C162, Folder 36)
- Jill Ker Conway "History as Inspired by the Tenth Muse" talk delivered at OBND luncheon. President 1975-85 April 11, 1983 (Box C34, Folder 37)
- Excerpts from Friends of Library Tapes Nov. 1, 1978 (Box C163)